<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: JavaScript | Deprecated Behaviour]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.tekerson.com/categories/javascript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.tekerson.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-01T19:03:24+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.tekerson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brenton Alker]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Entity Objects in JavaScript]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.tekerson.com/2015/07/31/entity-objects-in-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-31T18:26:37+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.tekerson.com/2015/07/31/entity-objects-in-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my last post I looked at Value Objects and how I might implement them in JavaScript. This time I&rsquo;m going to look at Entities. Entities are kind of the next rung on the ladder in the domain model. They can be composed of Value Objects.</p>

<p>Entities are <em>not</em> defined by their attributes in the same way as Value Objects, instead they have an enduring &ldquo;Identity&rdquo;. The canonical example is a person. A person isn&rsquo;t defined by their name, their age, their height, or any other attribute. Any of these can change and they are still the same person (barring any deep philisophical discussion). In software systems, this is usually implemented by assigning an arbitrary key that uniquely identifies the entity for its lifetime.</p>

<p>Where this key comes from is irrelevant to this discussion, but it is common for it to be a value that is generated in the persistence layer when the data is saved.</p>

<p>So, from this we could say that an entity is an instance with an identity and a collection of mutable attributes. Using a similar validation style to the one I used for Value Objects, I might write this in JavaScript like (yes, I&rsquo;m using a Car example, but I promise it&rsquo;s not the usual inheritence/composition example):</p>

<p>``` javascript
function Car(id, fields) {</p>

<pre><code>if (!id instanceof CarId) {
    throw new TypeError('Expected: CarId');
}
if (!fields instanceof CarFields) {
    throw new TypeError('Expected: CarFields');
}

this.id = id;
this.fields = fields;
return Object.freeze(this);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>But, I just said that entities are mutable, so, why am I still calling <code>Object.freeze</code>? Because, I want <em>this</em> object &ndash; the Entity &ndash; to be immutable, its <code>id</code> can&rsquo;t change but it&rsquo;s <code>fields</code> are still mutable; I&rsquo;m taking advantage of the shallow freeze semantics.</p>

<p>Side Note: If you&rsquo;ve been paying close attention, you may have noticed I&rsquo;m <code>throw</code>ing exceptions here instead of <code>return</code>ing them like last time. This is because I consider passing the wrong type to be a developer error, which is (hopefully) an exceptional situation, as opposed to a user entering an invalid value, which is to be expected.</p>

<p>Ignoring the <code>CarId</code>, which will be a Value Object similar to the previous post. The only interesting part left is the <code>CarFields</code> object. This will be slightly different to the Value Object and the Entity itself because it&rsquo;s mutable. So, its validation must be performed in the setters instead of the constructor. Using the common setter/getter pattern, it looks like:</p>

<p>``` javascript
function CarFields(model, odometer) {
  this.model(model);
  this.odometer(odometer);
}</p>

<p>CarFields.prototype.model = function(model) {
  if (model === undefined) {</p>

<pre><code>return this._model;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  if (!model instanceof CarMake) {</p>

<pre><code>throw new TypeError('Expected: CarModel');
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  this._model = model;
}</p>

<p>CarFields.prototype.odometer = function(odometer) {
  if (odometer === undefined) {</p>

<pre><code>return this._odometer;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  if (!odometer instanceof Distance) {</p>

<pre><code>throw new TypeError('Expected: Distance');
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  this._odometer = odometer;
}
```</p>

<p>Even though we now have setters, all of the values are still required in the constructor. This makes it impossible* to have a partially instantiated instance running around.</p>

<p>* &ldquo;Impossible&rdquo; is an optimistic take on it. If you want to assign invalid values directly to the &ldquo;internal&rdquo; fields, this won&rsquo;t protect you from yourself. This is JavaScript after all.</p>

<p>Another way of modeling the <code>CarEntity</code> is to have the fields as properties of the entity but leave the <code>id</code> as <code>null</code> until it is persisted, then updating it. The advantage of explicitly defining a <code>CarFields</code> is, once again, less mutation and preventing the creation of partially instantiated instances.</p>

<p>Before the data is persisted we have only <code>CarFields</code>. Once it is persisted <em>then</em> we have a <code>CarEntity</code>. The different types represent the different stages in the lifecycle and the two states are less easily confused.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Value Objects in JavaScript]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.tekerson.com/2015/07/15/value-objects-in-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-15T21:31:43+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.tekerson.com/2015/07/15/value-objects-in-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Value Objects are awesome! Many of the JavaScript applications I have encountered don&rsquo;t explicitly define their domain objects at all, instead passing primitives or raw object literals around.  Value Objects can define the values in an way that allows discussion and reasoning about the values being passed around. As well as a logical place to &ldquo;put code&rdquo;.</p>

<p>To explore their use, lets start by defining a simple Value Object &ndash; Distance &ndash; because I don&rsquo;t claim to be creative in these matters.</p>

<p>About the simplest way of defining a Value Object is like this.</p>

<p><code>javascript
function Distance(value, unit) {
  this.value = value;
  this.unit = unit;
}
</code></p>

<p>This is a good start and really isn&rsquo;t much more difficult that using object literals. Given the other advantages (that can be added incrementally), I don&rsquo;t see a down side.</p>

<p>But, but we can do better!</p>

<h2>Immutability</h2>

<p>My first step would be to make it immutable. Immutability is a great property to have, especially for things being passed around a lot. For Value Objects, I think it is a reasonable default.</p>

<p><code>javascript
function Distance(value, unit) {
  this.value = value;
  this.unit = unit;
  return Object.freeze(this);
}
</code></p>

<p>Now, <code>Object.freeze</code> isn&rsquo;t perfect. It only freezes the object itself; nested properties can still be mutated. But, I still think it&rsquo;s worth it to prevent accidental mutation, or third party code mutating your objects without your knowledge (I&rsquo;m looking at you, <code>ng-repeat</code>).</p>

<h2>Validation</h2>

<p>The next issue to look at is validation of the fields. <code>new Distance(12, 'parsecs');</code> would ostensibly give a valid <code>Distance</code>, but it probably wouldn&rsquo;t be very useful. We can use the constructor function to check the parameters, ensuring only valid values can be created. In this case, say &ndash; A distance is a positive whole number measured in centimetres, metres or kilometres.</p>

<p>It might be implemented this way:</p>

<p>``` javascript
function Distance(value, unit) {
  if (parseInt(value, 10) !== value) {</p>

<pre><code>return new Error('Distance Value is not a decimal number');
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  if (Distance.units.indexOf(unit) === -1) {</p>

<pre><code>return new Error('Distance Unit is not is not valid');
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  this.value = value;
  this.unit = unit;
  return Object.freeze(this);
}
Distance.units = [&lsquo;cm&rsquo;, &rsquo;m', &lsquo;km&rsquo;];
```</p>

<p>The decision to <code>return</code> the <code>Error</code>s instead of <code>throw</code> them is probably debatable, but I don&rsquo;t think validation errors are &ldquo;exceptional&rdquo; and find it composes better with higher order functions (eg. <code>map</code>, <code>filter</code>, <code>reduce</code>) which I generally use a lot of. Either way, the point is it won&rsquo;t get back a valid <code>Distance</code> object. And, since they are immutable, a valid <code>Distance</code> only ever be valid.</p>

<h2>Logic</h2>

<p>Once a Value Object is defined, it becomes a great place to put some logic. Normalization and comparison logic is a good candidate. For example, adding methods to compare two distances.</p>

<p><code>javascript
Distance.multipliers = [1, 100, 100000];
Distance.prototype.toCentimetres = function () {
  var multiplier = Distance.multipliers[Distance.units.indexOf(this.unit)];
  return this.value * multiplier;
};
Distance.prototype.isCloserThan = function (other) {
  return this.toCentimetres() &lt; other.toCentimetres();
};
</code></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also a good place to add domain logic; the application may define how far is considered &ldquo;walkable&rdquo;. By having the Value Object, it provides somewhere for this knowledge to go and prevents <code>if (distance &lt; 5)</code> being duplicated across the application.</p>

<p><code>javascript
Distance.walkable = new Distance(5, 'km');
Distance.prototype.isWalkable = function () {
  return this.isCloserThan(Distance.walkable);
};
</code></p>

<p>Then, when I decide I&rsquo;m too lazy to walk 5km, it only needs changing in one place.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
