<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ruby | Deprecated Behaviour]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.tekerson.com/categories/ruby/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.tekerson.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-12T23:47:22+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.tekerson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brenton Alker]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Search for the Holy Grail (Not Really)]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.tekerson.com/2007/01/13/search-for-the-holy-grail-not-really/"/>
    <updated>2007-01-13T02:17:38+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.tekerson.com/2007/01/13/search-for-the-holy-grail-not-really</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back from the Christmas/New Year festivities, I have been playing around (at a very basic level) with a few programming languages, with the goal of learning something new. All of the languages I have been playing with I have looked at in the past very briefly, but never ventured any deeper. This time I intend to pick one and hopefully learn it to a level where is might be useful.</p>

<p>Of the languages I am looking at, none are particularly unusual or oscure, they are all fairly common scripting languages used for web development.</p>

<p>My list so far consists of (in no particular order):</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://perl.org/">Perl</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://python.org/">Python</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://ruby-lang.org/">Ruby</a></p></li>
</ul>


<p>I have chosen these languages because as I said, they are common scripting languages, often used in web development. And I am looking to expand my repetoire. Learning a new language not only teaches the symantics of the language, but programming methods, structures and paradigms that can be implemented in any language.</p>

<p>With that in mind, I have decided to look at Ruby (at least for now).</p>

<p>Deciding to do web development with Ruby invariably leads to <a href="http://rubyonrails.org/">Ruby on Rails</a>. Not wanting to get (too) caught up in the hype, I decided to have a look at the raw language first. So, I had a read through the quite unusual (have a look and see) <a href="http://poignantguide.net/ruby/">Why's (Poignant) Guide to Ruby</a>. After sifting through this odd compilation to find the actual useful content (The humour -- cartoons, stories and the like -- throughout the book make it an interesting read, but maybe not the best reference manual) I had an overview of Ruby and liked what I saw.</p>

<p>After some initial playing around, reading up on the "raw" way of developing web sites in Ruby (raw text and with cgi extensions) I did end up installing rails.</p>

<p>I have experimented briefly with rails in the past, previously though, I had not bothered to learn anything at all about Ruby as a language. So, while the basic functionality of rails, the model/view/controller scaffolding was really impressive (it still is), if I wanted to do anything more adventurous, or if something broke, I was lost.</p>

<p>I am hoping that with a slightly better understanding of Ruby (and a willingness to learn the language this time) I will have more success with rails. If it doesn't work for me… I'll try somethign else.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
