<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Personal | Deprecated Behaviour]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.tekerson.com/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.tekerson.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-28T18:03:23+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.tekerson.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brenton Alker]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Design and a New Domain]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.tekerson.com/2008/04/19/new-design-and-a-new-domain/"/>
    <updated>2008-04-19T05:17:26+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.tekerson.com/2008/04/19/new-design-and-a-new-domain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, I finally bought myself a domain. You can now find me at my new home on the web: <a href="http://blog.tekerson.com/">blog.tekerson.com</a> (Not that you get a choice in the matter, the old domain redirects).
To go along with it, I've got a new design (for those of you that actually come back). I think it's better suited than the old one.
That is all!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Triumphant Return]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.tekerson.com/2008/02/21/a-triumphant-return/"/>
    <updated>2008-02-21T20:40:58+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.tekerson.com/2008/02/21/a-triumphant-return</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, a return anyway. I'm not exactly sure how triumphant it is.</p>

<p>Yes, that's right, I'm back. I've been away from my blog, my country and (for the most part) the Internet for over a month. I've been holidaying in Canada, doing some snowboarding, seeing the sights, doing the usual touristy stuff. As great as it was, all good things must come to an end, so here I am, back at home.</p>

<p>Some photos of my adventures can be found in <a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/Brenton.Alker">my gallery</a>. There are plenty more photo's which I might put up, and I might even get around to adding captions at some point.</p>

<p>On a technical note, about 2 days into my trip my server went down, and as it is unmanaged (read: sitting in my living room); I couldn't do anything about it, so it stayed down all month. Luckily there isn't anything on it more critical than my blog, but as a result Google has completely removed me from existence.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
